Once you understand what is happening to you,
your body and your chemistry,
and your mind, and you have a professional
supporting you throughout the process, not only
during the appointment, together you can teach
your body to respond differently. I would say
it is like a muscle: each time you feel
something but manage not to
react in the same way, it is as if that muscle
grows and raises your danger threshold.
Your body learns that the alarm was
unnecessary and that you were not in danger.
It does not need to sound the alarm, release
all that chemistry or cause
all that distress. Little by little we change
the pattern and the neural
connections, and your reactions. Like
everything in our body, we
have neuroplasticity, thankfully. We can
change the pattern through this process, repeatedly
strengthening that muscle, reducing the sense
of danger, bringing safety, responding and showing
your body that everything is all right. Those
alarms gradually switch off and you can feel
more in control, calmer and at peace.